Guide to the Tanner Lectures on Human Values at Stanford
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Tanner Lectures on Human Values at Stanford
1977-2014
SC1047
Stanford University
214 megabyte(s)
The materials consist of sound recordings, transcripts, and videorecordings of Tanner lectures delivered at Stanford.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Open for research.
Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
The Center for Ethics in Society collaborates with The Office of the President to host the Tanner Lectures on Human Values at Stanford.
Appointment as a Tanner lecturer is in recognition for uncommon achievement and outstanding abilities in the field of human values. The lecturers themselves come from the fields of philosophy, religion, the humanities, the sciences, the creative arts, and learned professions, or from leadership in public or private affairs. The lectureships are international and intercultural and transcend ethnic, national, religious, and ideological distinctions. Past Tanner lecturers at Stanford include: Jared Diamond, Dorothy Allison, Paul Krugman, Mary Robinson, Harry Frankfurt, Avishai Margalit, David Brion Davis, and Glenn Loury.
The purpose of the Tanner Lectures is to advance and reflect upon the scholarly and scientific learning relating to human values. This intention embraces the entire range of values pertinent to the human condition, interest, behavior, and aspiration. The lectures are published in an annual volume.
The Tanner Lectures were established by the late American scholar, industrialist, and philanthropist, Obert Clark Tanner. In creating the lectureships, Tanner said, "I hope these lectures will contribute to the intellectual and moral life of mankind. I see them simply as a search for a better understanding of human behavior and human values. This understanding may be pursued for its own intrinsic worth, but it may also eventually have practical consequences for the quality of personal and social life."
Stanford is proud to be one of the nine distinguished universities to host the Tanner Lectures. The Tanner lectureships, which are comprised of annual lectures and seminars, are held at nine universities including Cambridge, Harvard, Michigan, Oxford, Princeton, The University of California, Utah, Yale, and Stanford.
Scope and Contents note
The materials consist of sound recordings, transcripts, and videorecordings of Tanner lectures delivered at Stanford.
Arrangement note
The materials are arranged chronologically.
Access Terms
Bowen, William G.; Cavell, Stanley.; Cohen, Gerald.; Cooper, John M. (John Madison), 1939-; Danner, Mark.; Dworkin, Ronald.; Foucault, Michel.; Fraser, Nancy.; Fried, Charles.; Gauthier, David.; Gould, Stephen Jay; Gutmann, Amy.; Herman, Barbara.; Hill, Thomas E., Jr.; Kornai, Janos.; McMillan, Evelyn.; Meyer, Leonard B.; Ostrom, Elinor.; Renfrew, Colin.; Stone, Alan.; Striker, Gisela.; Taylor, Charles.; Lectures.; Social values.
Collection Contents
- Recordings, 1979-2014
  - Foucault, Michel, "Omnes et Singulatim: Towards a Criticism of ‘Political Reason'", 1979 Oct 10, 16; 1.42-1.43; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Fried, Charles, "Is Liberty Possible?", 1981 May 14, 18; 1.1-1.2; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Stone, Alan, "Psychiatry and Morality", 1982 Mar 31, Apr 5; 1.3-1.4; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Gauthier, David, "The Incompleat Egoist", 1983 May 4, 10; 1.5-1.6; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Meyer, Leonard B., " Music and Ideology in the Nineteenth Century", 1984 May 17, 21; 1.7-1.9; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Cavell, Stanley, "The Uncanniness of the Ordinary", 1986 Apr 3, 8; 1.10-1.12; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Striker, Gisela, "Greek Ethics and Moral Theory", 1987 May 14, 17; 1.13-1.14; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Dworkin, Ronald, 1988 May 5, 10; 1.15-1.18; 4 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Gould, Stephen Jay, 1989 Mar 13-14; 1.19-1.22; 4 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Kornai, János, I., "Market Socialism Revisited" II. "The Soviet Union’s Road to a Free Economy: Comments of an Outside Observer", 1991 Jan 15, 17; 1.23-1.24; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Cohen, Gerald, "Incentives, Inequality, and Community", 1991 May 21, 23; 1.25-1.27; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Taylor, Charles, "Modernity and the Rise of the Public Sphere", 1992 Feb 25; 1.28; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Renfrew, Colin, "Archeology of Identity", 1993 Mar 31; 1.29-1.30; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Hill Jr., Thomas E., "Respect for Humanity", 1994 Apr 26, 28; 1.31-1.33; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 31-33)
  - Gutmann, Amy, "Responding to Racial Injustice", 1995 May 16, 18; 1.34-1.37; 4 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Fraser, Nancy, "Social Justice in the Age of Identity Politics: From Redistribution to Recognition", 1996 Apr 30; 2.38; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Fraser, Nancy, "Social Justice in the Age of Identity Politics: Toward an Integrated Conception of Justice", 1996 May 2; 2.39; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Herman, Barbara, "The Practice of Moral Judgment: Responsibility and Moral Competence", 1997 May; 2.40; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Herman, Barbara, "The Practice of Moral Judgment: Can Virtue Be Taught?", 1997 Jun; 2.41; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Danner, Mark, "Torture and the Forever War: Living in the State of Exception"
    - "Imposing the State of Exception: Constitutional Dictatorship, Torture and Us", 1 computer file(s) (M4V)
      Contact Public Services (e-mail: speccollref@stanford.edu) for information on accessing this digital object.
      - Discussion, 1 computer file(s) (M4V)
    - "Naturalizing the State of Exception: Terror, Fear and the War Without End", 1 computer file(s) (M4V)
      - Discussion, 1 computer file(s) (M4V)
  - Ostrom, Elinor, "The Challenge of Sustainability: Frameworks", 2011 Feb 16
    Elinor Ostrom is the Arthur F. Bentley Professor of Professor of Political Science at Indiana University. She is also the Founding Director of the Center for the Study of Institutional Diversity at Arizona State University. Ostrom is a member of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the National Academy of Sciences, and the American Philosophical Society. She is the recipient of many distinguished awards and has authored (and/or co-authored) numerous books including Trust and Reciprocity: Interdisciplinary Lessons from Experimental Research (2003); The Commons in the New Millennium: Challenges and Adaptations (2003); The Samaritan’s Dilemma: The Political Economy of Development Aid (2005); Understanding Institutional Diversity (2005); and Understanding Knowledge as a Commons: From Theory to Practice (2007).
  - Ostrom, Elinor, "The Challenge of Sustainability: Puzzles", 2011 Feb 17
  - Bowen, William G., "The Productivity Problem in Higher Education", 2012-10-10
  - Bowen, William G., "Prospects for an Online Learning Fix", 2012-10-11
  - Cooper, John M. (John Madison), 1939-, "Ancient Philosophies as a Way of Life: Socrates", 2012-01-25
  - Cooper, John M. (John Madison), 1939-, "Platonist Philosophy as a Way of Life: Plotinus", 2012-01-26
  - Lehmann, Nicholas, "The Turn Against Institutions", 2014-01-15
  - Lehmann, Nicholas, "What Transactions Can't Do", 2014-01-16
  - Lehmann, Nicholas, "What Transactions Can't Do" discussion, 2014-01-17
- Transcripts
- Posters, 1977-2014 (Box 3)